A Guide to the Mary Lee Chapman Elkins collection, 1783-1966
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Mary Lee Chapman Elkins collection, 1783-1966
The Library of Virginia
27856
5.6 cu. ft. and 16 boxes
Mary Lee Chapman Elkins
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ethel C. E. Lau of Norristown, Pennsylvania.
Biographical Information
Mary Lee Chapman was born 13 September 1862 in York, Pennsylvania. She married Harvey Lincoln Elkins (1862-1935), a broker of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, on 27 March 1889 and they had three children. Mary Lee Chapman Elkins conducted extensive genealogical research into her family's history. She died 3 August 1916 in Philadelphia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1783-1966, of Mary Lee Chapman Elkins (1862-1916) containing her correspondence and genealogical research files, as well as the bills of sale, correspondence, deeds, diary, and other papers of her ancestor James Riddick Wilson (1793-1852) of Smithfield, Virginia. Papers also include materials on and records of Norfolk and Norfolk County, Virginia. Also includes papers of Ethel C. E. Lau (1895-1968), who transcribed and arranged most of the papers.Mary Lee Chapman Elkins. Papers, 1783-1966. Accession 27856.
Contents List
- Obituaries, notes, receipts, and miscellaneous papers, 1899-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- General correspondence, 1888-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, January-March 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, April-July 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, August-September 1909 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, October-December 1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, January-March 1910 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, May-August 1910 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, September-November 1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, January-September 1914 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, October-December 1914 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, January-February 1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, March 1915 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, April 1915 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, May-June 1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, July-October 1915 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, November-December, undated 1915 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Genealogy: Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correpondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Genealogy: Ethel Chapman Elkins Lau correpondence, 1930, 1945-1956, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correspondence, transcriptions, volume I, correspondence with Fanny Blow Hunter, 1909-1911 (Box 4)
- Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correspondence, transcriptions, volume II, correspondence with Fanny Blow Hunter, 1911-1916 (Box 4)
- Mary Lee Chapman Elkins correspondence,transcriptions, volume III, general correspondence, 1909-1916 (Box 5)
- Mary Lee Chapman Elkins and Ethel C. E. Lau correspondence, transcriptions, volume IV, general correspondence, 1909-1946 (Box 5)
- Ballard family research, 1490-1783 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Blow family research, 1808-1894 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Burroughs family research (including Wright family), 1563-1777 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Byrd family research (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Conner family research, 1707-1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Lawson family research, 1668-1701 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Mallory family research, 1643-1957 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Mason family research, 1583-1714 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Moseley family research, 1655-1794 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Parker family research, 1654-1814 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Phripp family research, 1644, 1744-1798 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Proby family research, 1622-1839 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Riddick family research, 1714-1907 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Thelaball family research, 1707-1767 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Trevethan family research, 1675-1738 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Wilson family research, 1620-1915 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Wilson family research (including Byrd family), 1656-1772 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Wright family research, 1540-1721 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Wright family research (including Jones, Mallory families), 1590-1851 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Wright family research, 1608-1913 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Wright family research, 1627-1849 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Wright family research (including Phripp family), 1653-1862 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Family research: Burgess, Carney, Conner, Craford, Wright, Cary (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Family research: Byrd, Chapman, Conner, Phripp, Wilson, Wright (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Family research: Church, Phillips, Wilson, Wright, Mason (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Family research: Conner, Craford, Mason, Thelaball, Wilson, Wright, Baker (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Family research: Phillips, Seawell, Wilson, Wright, Conner, Mason (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Family research: Bromley, Chapman, Green, Mason, Phillips, Wilson, Wright (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Family research: Chapman, Church, Conner, Craford, Mason, Wilson, Wright (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Family research: Chapman, Moseley, Wilson, Wright, Conner, Church, Phripp, Mason (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Family research: Conner, Craford, Martin, Mason, Phillips, Phripp, Rogers, Wilson, Wright (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Family research: Mason, Phripp, Seawell, Willoughby (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Family research: Mason, Phripp, Rogers, Seawell, Willoughby, Wright (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Family research: Mason, Phripp, Wright, Church, Griffin (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Family research: Mason, Wright (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Family research: Wilson, Wright, Riddick, Chapman, Mason (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Family research: names from Hakluyt's Principal Voyages of the British Nation (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Norfolk's Silver Mace (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Old Saint Paul's caldendar, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Virginia land patents (folder 1 of 3) (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Virginia land patents (folder 2 of 3) (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Virginia land patents (folder 3 of 3) (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Genealogy research: North Carolina Historical and Genealogical Register, volumes 1-3, excerpts (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Genealogy research: miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Early Norfolk County records, Portsmouth, Virginia, volume I (Box 11)
- Early Norfolk County records, Portsmouth, Virginia, volume II (Box 11)
- Early Norfolk County records, Portsmouth, Virginia, volume III (Box 12)
- Early Norfolk County records, Portsmouth, Virginia, volume IV (Box 12)
- Early Norfolk County records, Portsmouth, Virginia, volume V (Box 13)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: diary, part I, 1819-1820 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: diary, part II, 2-23 September 1821 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: diary, part III, 1834-1846 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: Memorandum for my Children, 1846 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: letters, 1840-1852, 1870 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: promissory notes, 1811-1850 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: receipts, 1817-1857 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: photographs (Box 14, Folder 8)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: miscellaneous papers, 1784-1916 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: transcriptions, volume I (Box 15)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: transcriptions, volume II (Box 15)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: bills of sale, 1788, 1839-1858 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: deeds, 1783-1798 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: deeds, 1813-1819 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: deeds, 1820-1825 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: deeds, 1831-1839 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: deeds, 1843-1849 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- James Riddick Wilson papers: deeds, 1850-1871 (Box 16, Folder 7)